Hi. Welcome back to the Wheel of Life
series...  online retreat, and today
we're going to do, for session six. I'm
sorry (laughs) we're going to do a meditation. And
during this online retreat we're
discussing three kinds--actually four
kinds--of meditation you can do to warm
up for your real meditation. And of course we did
the seven preparation steps already. Now
today we're going to do what's called
"the eight technique meditations." And
these meditations help you improve your
meditation technique. They're not
actually meditations themselves. It's
like we are just building a stronger
microscope, but we're not looking at
anything with the microscope.
So these meditations are kind of
exciting. And kind of sexy. But, please,
they are not real meditations. You are
just sharpening the knife; you are not
cutting the fruit yet. Cutting the fruit is
real meditation. Sharpening the knife is
just improving your concentration. If you
want to say it a different way, you can
say these eight technique meditations
help you reach shamatha. And shamatha
means ... literally it means
"peacefulness," but it means the kind of
perfect focus you're going to have to
develop if you want to see emptiness
later. So personally, in my daily
meditation, I mix up different
preliminaries. Some days I feel like
doing the seven preliminaries because
I'd like to start with my teacher.
And that's a very powerful karma for
starting your meditation. But sometimes before
meditation, I like to use these eight
technique meditations. Sometimes I want
to call them "getting quiet" meditations.
And the goal of these eight is to get
quieter, and quieter, and quieter. And then
you shift to the real meditation. So in
session six, today, we're just going to
practice those eight "getting quieter
technique meditations," and then in
tomorrow's segment--session seven--I'll
show you how to use those eight to get
into your meditation, and then do a real
meditation.
The picture that we use for these
eight is a picture of the sky and the
sea.
And you'll understand that more as
we go through these meditations.
These
are traditionally divided into two sets
of four and four.
And the nickname for them
in Tibetan Buddhism is sam suk (BSAM GZUGS), sam
suk.
sam (BSAM) is short for samten (BSAM GTAN),
and
samten, like dhyana in Sanskrit, and
the word chan or zen comes from that.
So actually all meditations
are dhyana, but the first four are,
together, traditionally they are called
samten shi (BSAM GTAN BZHI)--"the four meditation levels."
And as you know if you studied the Lion's
Dance, these these are divided into
cause meditations and result meditations.
"Cause meditation" means if you do these
four samtens or dhyanas over and over
in this life--many, many, many times--when
you die, you could be born into what we
call the form realm. Form is also a
nickname, and it means the realm of
beings who look like superheroes. So in
that realm everybody looks like Iron Man,
or Thor, or Wonder Woman. They have very, very beautiful
forms, so it's called form realm meditation.
Then we go to the second set of four. So,
the whole eight are called sam suk. The
sam (BSAM) means the samten--four kinds of
meditation to reach the form realm
rebirth of Thor and Iron Man. And to
call the second set suk (GZUGS) is very
confusing, because suk means "physical
form." But really those realms are suk-me (GZUGS MED)--
formless realms. And you are born without any
gross physical body there, if you do these four
meditations. Whether you become poor or
whether you become a person who is just
a brain and no body,
you are still in sansara, and there's a lot of
suffering there. So we don't do these
meditations to reach those two realms. We
use these meditations to get quieter, and
quieter, and quieter so we can do a
higher meditation. So when you say "we're trying to
reach shamatha,"
it doesn't mean peace in the sense of
Nirvana; it means peace in the sense of
perfect concentration. And perfect quiet.
So let's start. Take your meditation
position. Make sure you're comfortable--
don't start your meditation until you
are really comfortable. Stomach is a
little bit ... lower abdomen is a little bit
pushed in. The perfect way to do that,
when you exhale, then push a little extra
air out, and that will also prevent problems
with too much prana build-up. Shoulders
back, chest out, the hands come back on
the legs a little bit. Face is calm. Many of
us, when we concentrate, we scowl. So try
to concentrate without scowling. I like
to play music. When I play sitar, for
example, I scowl
because I'm concentrating. So during
meditation, especially these eight, try to
concentrate but don't scowl. The face
is very pleasant, relaxed, little smile.
Now usually we start a meditation by
watching our breath for about ten breaths.
But it's traditional--especially in the
"Lion's Dance"--to start this meditation in
a completely different way. So before you
start the eight, we're going to listen to
any subtle sounds in this room. It might
be the sound of a few cars outside, it
might be the sound of some family
members in your apartment.
The sound of a refrigerator is very
typical in most houses. In this room
right now,
at the Sedona College of International
Management and the headquarters of ACI,
we have air conditioning going right now.
So whatever sound you have available in
your place, please put your mind on that
sound. I enjoy the image of putting my
head on a pillow. When I put my head on
my pillow at night, I so enjoy that
moment. And the head goes down to the
pillow and it stays there. You don't
raise your head, put it back, raise your
head, put it back, raise your head ...
you don't do that. So for this sound
meditation before we do the eight technique
meditations, please relax your mind on
that sound in your room like you are
putting your head on a pillow and leave
it there.
Here we go. Stanley and I will put our
minds on the air conditioning. Again, personally
I like to time the parts of my
meditation. I might do ten breaths on each
part or twenty. People ask me, "Isn't that a
distraction, when you think about your
breath when you're supposed to be thinking
about the air conditioner?" But if you
practice meditation every day, the ten
breaths becomes natural to you, and it
won't be a distraction. Okay, here we go.
Try to keep your mind on the sound.
Now we're going to go into the first of
the eight technique meditations. And
please put your mind on your heartbeat.
For me, it feels like I'm in my head and
I'm kind of feeling my heart beat in
my chest. And I'm not inside the heart,
I'm just observing the heart. If you meditate
a lot and if you have a quiet place to
meditate, you can follow your heartbeat--
the pulse--in your ears. So here we
go.
Relax. Don't rush. Just have fun.
Please remember to push the breath out
at the exhale--at the end of the exhale, until your
lower abdomen tightens, very slightly--all
throughout these meditations. OK. Let's
focus on our heartbeats, and try not to
think of other things. These eight
meditations are described as dropping
the last level and moving up to the next
level. Each level is more quiet than the last
level--higher, higher quiet. So you almost
consciously say, "I'm going to
stop listening to the air conditioner
and I'm going to move up to a quieter
heartbeat."
So try to stay on the heartbeat and try
not to listen to the air-conditioner
anymore. You should feel like you're
getting quieter and quieter.
Now we're going to go even more
quiet--the second of the eight technique
meditations. Let's go inside our heart. We
will still be listening to the heartbeat,
but it will feel like the walls of our
little meditation room are beating
because we're inside the heart.
Now the inside of the heart is kind of
wet and gooey, but for this meditation
you have to imagine that inside the
heart is a lovely, elegant meditation room.
Sunlight is coming through the windows.
You have a very comfortable meditation
seat. It's super quiet, but the walls
around you--the heart walls--are beating.
So now drop down from your head and
enter your heart. And let's stay in that
more quiet place with the heart beating
around us.
Now we'll go to the third technique
meditation, the third part of the form
realm meditation. And imagine there's a
meditation room at the center of your
meditation room. I like to think of it like a
very expensive apartment on the top of a
tall apartment building. And all the
windows are glass, and there's a room at
the center of the apartment. And I go
into that room and I close the door.
There's still some sunlight coming in
and it's still a beautiful, elegant room
with good air, but the heart beating in
the walls, now it sounds very far away--
very faint. Okay, here we go to the
meditation room at the center of the
heart.
Even more quiet.
Now I'd like you to imagine a small
table at your side--inside this inner
room of the heart. And sitting on that
table is a small pot of sugar--white
sugar. And you lift off the lid of the
sugar pot, and with the third finger of
your left hand, you just touch the sugar,
slightly. And you lift the finger out and
there's a few grains of sugar on the tip
of your finger. Focus on one of those grains of
sugar, and then think to yourself, "Oh, I
would like to be inside that sugar
crystal." It's super quiet. It's also super
anonymous--who's going to find you in the
whole room inside a sugar crystal?
In the whole world, in the whole universe,
it's a tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny, little place.
"If I go inside there, I'll be super quiet.
No one would ever find me there." So
imagine you are opening a door into the
sugar crystal and you
kind of squeeze your mind through that
little door. Then you're very surprised.
Inside it's a third meditation
room--kind of large and very
comfortable. Light is coming in through
the edges of the crystal, and you sit
down and meditate inside there. If
someone came into your main meditation
room at this moment, in your
house,
how could they ever bother you? You are
in a single ... it's like you're
in a single atom in a huge room. So let's
go inside and meditate. Very, very quiet
inside--no more heartbeat at all.
Now let's take a challenge. In the fifth of
the eight technique meditations, which is
the first of the formless realm
meditations, we take a challenge. Can you
fit the whole Pacific Ocean inside of
that sugar crystal? So now you
become the Pacific Ocean. You are
thousands of miles wide. You're a few
miles deep. You cover a good part of the
whole world. And Pacific Ocean--"pacific" means
"peaceful." So you are this deep, peaceful,
blue ocean.
Totally silent.
Let's go even bigger and broader.
Let's add the whole blue sky to the blue
water. This is the picture we used for
this meditation. "I am the entire blue sky.
And I am the entire blue Pacific Ocean. I
stretch from the bottom of the ocean to
the top of the sky." Totally peaceful.
Totally calm.
What could be more quiet than that?
"What if I just turned my whole mind off,
like a light?" It's actually ... technically,
it's not possible--but let's pretend. "I'm
going to turn my mind off like a light and
this will be more quiet than anything
before--like completely unconscious." Watch
your mind. Keep it super quiet--no talking
in the mind at all. If a thought comes
through, if some random image comes
through, if some interruption from the
outside comes into the mind, go to
it and block it. Tell it to shut up.
Push it out of the mind. Here we go.
Now we're going to go to meditation
level eight--the highest level of the
formless realm meditations, which lead
you to the formless realm if you do them
a lot in this life. "Now I'm also going to
shut up the part of my mind which is
watching my mind to see if my mind is
thinking about anything."
"Now if random thoughts or ideas come through
my mind, no one will be there to hear
them," which is a deeper quiet place.
Nobody even watching. Let's try.
Now let's dedicate the meditation--these
eight technique meditations--just with a wish
in your heart that all the people
in the world would find this kind of
peace and quiet.
Slowly open your eyes. Take a stretch. See
you tomorrow in the next session.